A Finding Aid to the Staempfli Gallery Records, 1958-1992, in the Archives of American Art AAA.staegall2
Archives of American Art
Staempfli Gallery records
1958-1992
AAA.staegall2
Archives of American Art
5.2 Linear feet
The Staempfli Gallery records measure 5.2 linear feet and date from 1958 to 1992. Scattered administrative and financial records, correspondence, sales invoices, inventory records, and exhibition catalogs document the business activities of this New York gallery.
Staempfli Gallery (New York, N.Y.)
Provenance
Exhibition Catalogs were donated in 1989 by Philip Bruno, co-director of Staempfli Gallery. Additional records of the Staempfli Gallery were donated in 2010 by Candida Steel, George Staempfli's daughter and in 2014 by Robert Aichele, a private dealer in Sacramento, California, who purchased the letters from Barbara Staempfli, George Staempfli's widow.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires and appointment and is limited to the Archives’ Washington, D.C. Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Historical Note
Staempfli Gallery was established by George Staempfli in 1959 in New York City and specialized in modern art by European and American artists. George William Staempfli (1910-1999) was born in Bern, Switzerland, and moved to the United States in 1935. He worked at M. Knoedler & Company and was curator of paintings the Museum of Fine Arts in Houston from 1954 to 1956. He founded Staempfli Gallery in 1959 and exhibited the work of a variety of artists. Phillip A. Bruno served as co-director for over twenty years, until the gallery officially closed in 1988. George Staempfli retired to Annapolis, Maryland, in 1992, and lived there until his death in 1999.
Scope and Content Note
The Staempfli Gallery records measure 5.2 linear feet and date from 1958 to 1992. Scattered administrative and financial records, correspondence, sales invoices, inventory records, and exhibition catalogs document the business activities of this New York gallery.
Administrative records include certificates of incorporation, minutes and by-laws, lease forms, and an employment agreement between Staempfli Gallery and its director Phillip A. Bruno.
Correspondence is with Joan Brown, David Park, Elmer Bischoff, and Roland Peterson. One file of general correspondence includes other letters to and from George Staempfli.
Financial records of are not comprehensive and primarily document financial activities from the late 1970s and 1980s. Included are annual financial reports, income tax records, records of commissions, and shipping invoices. During the mid-1980s the gallery had a sales tax audit, and many of the records of the gallery, including correspondence and notes regarding sales, sales invoices, and shipping records from 1980 to 1985 were gathered and can be found within these files.
Sales invoices are from 1986 to 1988 and include sales from the Chicago International Art Expo and Art Basel. Additional information regarding sale of artwork can also be found in the inventory records which consist of three inventory lists and an inventory card file. The inventory card file was maintained during the entire operation of the gallery from 1959 to 1992. Each work of art was given its own card and was filed alphabetically by artist. Researchers should note that cards for artists with a last name beginning with C through K were not included in the donation to the Archives of American Art.
Exhibition catalogs document one-person shows of modern American and European painters and sculptors, and several group exhibitions are also included. A few of the catalogs include annotations regarding price and sale of the exhibited works. Also found is one theater program inscribed to Geroge Steampfli by the artist Paul Delvaux.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 5 series:
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1958-1991 (Box 1; 8 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1959-1989 (Box 1; 6 folders)
Series 3: Financial Records, 1959-1991 (Box 1; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 4: Sales Records, 1986-1988 (Box 2; 8 folders)
Series 5: Inventory Records, 1959-1992 (Boxes 2-5; 3.2 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1959-1988 (Boxes 5-6; 0.7 linear feet)
Bischoff, Elmer, 1916-1991; Brown, Joan, 1938-1990; Bruno, Phillip A.; Park, David, 1911-1960; Peterson, Roland; Staempfli, George W.; Art galleries, Commercial--New York (State)--New York; Art, Modern; Financial records; Painters; Sculptors; Tax records
- Administrative Records, 1958-1991; Series 1; (Box 1; 8 folders)
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains scattered administrative records of the Staempfli Gallery including certificates of incorporation, minutes and by-laws, lease forms, letters of resignations from various gallery staff, and an employment agreement between Staempfli Gallery and its director Phillip A. Bruno. Also of note is a list of suggestions for future gallery operations from 1967, and a biographical chronology for George Staempfli.
  Arrangement note
  Files are arranged alphabetically.
  - Agreement between Staempfli Gallery, Inc. and Phillip A. Bruno, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificates of Incorporation, 1958-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronology for George W. Staempfli, circa 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters of Resignation, circa 1959-1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mailing List for Forum Sale, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Minutes and By-Laws, 1959-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Renewal Lease Form, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Suggestions for Future Operations, circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1959-1989; Series 2; 6 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence is with artists Elmer Bischoff, Joan Brown, David Park, and Roland Petersen. One additional file contains general office correspondence to and from George Staempfli. Additional correspondence can be found in Series 3: Financial Records.
  - Elmer Bischoff, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Joan Brown, 1961; undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - David Park, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Roland Petersen, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General Correspondence, 1960-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Financial Records, 1959-1991; Series 3; (Box 1; 0.9 linear feet)
  This series contains the financial records of the Staempfli Gallery. These records are not comprehensive and primarily document financial activities from the late 1970s and 1980s. Included are annual financial reports, income tax records, and records of commissions to Phillip A. Bruno. Also found are shipping invoices and other miscellaneous invoices for framing, books, and appraisals. During the mid-1980s the gallery had a sales tax audit, and many of the sales records of the gallery from 1980 to 1985 were compiled for the audit and can be found within these files. Types of documents found among the audit records include correspondence and notes regarding sales, sales invoices, and shipping records. Also found are scattered insurance documents, banking records, receipts, and records of expenses.
  Files are arranged alphabetically. Items are arranged chronologically within each folder. Documents within the sales tax audit files have been kept in the original order.
  - Analysis of George W. Staempfli Account, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Banking Documents, 1970-1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Blue Cross Blue Shield Records, 1982, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Budget of Estimated Monthly Expenses, circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Computation of Commissions Due to Philip A. Bruno, 1965-1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Debenture and Promissory Note to Emily Staempfli, 1965, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Documents for IRS Examination, 1973; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Financial Reports, 1959-1988; (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 23-28)
  - "G/L General Ledger" Database Printout, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Income Tax Documents, Miscellaneous, circa 1961-1978 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Income Tax Returns, 1967-1990; (12 folders) (Box 1, Folder 31-42)
  - Receipts, 1964-1979, 1988-1989; (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
  - Sales Tax Audit, 1980-1986; (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 45-50)
  - Schedule of Expenses, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Shipping Invoices and Miscellaneous Charges, 1986-1988; (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 52-55)
  - Stock Certificates, 1959-1969 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Workers Compensation and Employers Liability Insurance Policy, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Sales Records, 1986-1988; Series 4; (Box 2; 8 folders)
  This series contains sales invoices from 1986 to 1988, including sales from the Chicago International Art Expo and Art Basel. Many invoices include handwritten annotations and attached shipping receipts.
  Sales invoices are arranged by sales invoice number. Researchers should note that additional sales invoices from the 1980s can be found within the sales tax audit files in Series 2: Financial Records. Information regarding sale of artwork can also be found in Series 4: Inventory Records.
  - Sales Invoices, nos. 4726-4922, 1986-1988; (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Sales Invoices, nos. 8701-8726, Chicago International Art Expo, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Sales Invoices, nos. 8727-8741, Basel, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Inventory Records, 1959-1992; Series 5; (Boxes 2-5; 3.2 linear feet)
  Inventory records consist of three inventory lists of artwork and an inventory card file. The inventory card file was maintained during the entire operation of the gallery from 1959 to 1992. Each work of art was given its own card and was filed alphabetically by artist. Information typically found on the card includes artist name, title of work, date, size, medium, and inventory number. Most of the cards also have an attached photograph of the artwork, and include sale information such as date of sale, purchaser, price, and sales invoice number.
  Researchers should note that the inventory card file is incomplete. Cards for artists with a last name beginning with C through K were not included in the donation to the Archives of American Art. The exception is two artists whose cards were misfiled and are now placed in the correct alphabetical order.
  - Inventory Lists, 1967, 1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Inventory Card File (Box 2)
    - Adam, Henri-Georges, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Adams, Robert, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Aeppli, Eva, circa 1959 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Aiko, Miyawaki, circa 1968-1989 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Alderfer-Abbott, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Allan, Bill, circa 1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Anuszkiewicz, Richard, circa 1960s (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Appel, Karel, 1960-1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Arita, Akira, 1981-1984; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - Arp, Hans, 1976, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Aschauer, Alfred, circa 1968-1987 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Bailey, William, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Barraud, Francois, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Baruchello, Gianfranco, circa 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Baschet, Bernard and Francois, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Bassman, Lillian, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Bauchant, A., 1985 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Bauermeister, Mary, 1969-1985 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Baxter, Robert, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Berke, Hubert, circa 1959 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Bill, Max, 1969-1972 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Bing, Berenice, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Bissler, Julius, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Black, Frederick, circa 1959 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Boynton, James, circa 1960-1989 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Brancusi, Constantin, 1959-1967 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Braque, Georges, circa 1959 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Britell, Richard, 1977-1989 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Bro, circa 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Broderson, Morris, 1959-1988 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Brooks, James, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Brosen, Frederick, 1981-1988 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - De Medina, Robles, circa 1962 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Gay, Walter, circa 1959 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Lamis, Leroy, circa 1966-1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Laurens, Henri, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Lawton, Nancy, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Leger, Fernand, circa 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Light, Alvin, circa 1959-1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Lionni, Leo, 1977-1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Loberg, Robert, 1959-1982 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Lojselet, A., 1977-1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Loosili, Arthur, 1969-1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Love, James, circa 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Luginbuhl, Bernhard, 1959-1963 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Maeda, Josaku, 1971-1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Magee, Alan, 1983-1990 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Magritte, Rene, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Maillol, Aristide, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Mann, Robert, 1974-1975, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Manzu, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Marcote, Carlos, 1977-1990 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Marini, Marino, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Matisse, Henri, circa 1963 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Matta, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Mauke, Rudolf, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - McEwan, Rory, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Meadows, Barnard, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Meier-Denninghoff, Brigitte, circa 1962-1991 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Metzler, Keith, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Miki, Tomio, 1965-1976 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Minguzzi, Luciano, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Mira, Victor, 1980-1991 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Miro, Joan, circa 1962 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Modigliani, Amedeo, circa 1982 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Mola, circa 1968-1971; (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
    - Moore, Henry, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Morandi, Giorgio, circa 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Moswitzer, Gerhardt, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Muller, Erich, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Muller, Jan, 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Munoz, Lucio, 1964-1991 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Nagaoka, Kunito, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Nagare, Masayuki, circa 1959-1988; (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 41-43)
    - Nakano, Emiko, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Nakoneczny, Michael, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Neri, Manuel, 1960-1974 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Nevelson, Mike, circa 1961-1976 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Nicholson, Ben, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Noguchi, Isamu, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Nolde, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Norrman, Gunnar, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Oceanic Art, 1969-1989 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Okada, Kenzo, circa 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Onosato, Toshinobu, circa 1965-1988 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Paquette, Gregory, 1978-1986 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Park, David, 1959-1988; (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
    - Pascin, Jules, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Paul, Peter, circa 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Petersen, Roland, circa 1963-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Pevsner, Antoine, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Pfriem, Bernard, 1974-1989 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Philips, Jonathan, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Philipps, Kris, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Picasso, Pablo, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Piqueras, Jorge, 1962-1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Pita, Gerardo, 1984-1992; (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 14-15)
    - Pollock, Jackson, circa 1963 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Ponc, Joan, circa 1982-1989 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Prantl, Karl, 1967-1987 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Prestini, James, 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Quintanilla, Isabel, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Ray, Man, circa 1964 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Rebeyrolle, Paul, circa 1959 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Renoir, Auguste, circa 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Richter, Vjenceslav, 1968-1975 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Rivera, Manuel, 1963-1988 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Rivero, Fernando, 1985-1988 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Rodin, Auguste, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Rodriguez-Larrain, Emilio, 1961-1988 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Rouault, Georges, circa 1959 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Sairo, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Saite, Takashi, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Salemme, Attilio, circa 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Schlamminger, Karl, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Schmidt-Rottluff, Karl, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Schreiter, Gerhardt, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Schultz, Richard, 1960-1988 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Sekine, Nobuo, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Sekine, Yoshio, circa 1965-1988 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Sempere, Eusebio, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Shahn, Ben, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Shechter, Laura, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Shinoda, Morio, circa 1966 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Shulman, Morris, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Signac, Paul, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Sinton, Nell, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Smith, David, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Soto, 1959-1988 (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Soutine, Chaim, undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Sovak, Pravoslav, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Staempfli, George, 1975-1988 (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Steinberg, Saul, circa 1976-1979 (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Stone and Crystal, circa 1967-1976 (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Stromeyer, David, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Sugiyama, M., 1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Szekessy, Karin, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Takamatsu, Jiro, 1967-1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Takis, circa 1959 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Tamayo, Rufino, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Tanaka, Atsuko, circa 1964 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Tapies, A., 1971-1980s (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Tchelitchew, Paul, 1964-1970 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Tiepolo, Giovanni Domenico, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Tinguely, Jean, 1959-1987 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Tobey, Mark, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Tolstedt, Lowell, 1981-1984 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Toral, Cristobal, 1971-1991 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Turnbull, Peter, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Twardowicz, Stanley, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Uhlmann, Hans, 1959-1976 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Utillo, Maurice, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Valenti, Celestino, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Van Gogh, Vincent, circa 1959 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Van Isacker, Ignace, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Vara, Enrique, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Walters, Carl, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Wasserstein, Julius, 1959-1989 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Westwood, Bryan, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Wiley, William, 1961-1986 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Wunderlich, Paul, circa 1969-1990; (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 27-28)
    - Yagi, Kazuo, 1971-1985 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Zogbaum, Wilfred, circa 1960-1988 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Printed Material, 1959-1988; Series 6; (Boxes 5-6; 0.7 linear feet)
  This series contains an incomplete run of catalogs for exhibitions held at the Staempfli Gallery. Also found are a few scattered catalogs for special Steampfli Gallery exhibitions held in Los Angeles and Houston. Most of the catalogs are for one-person shows of modern American and European painters and sculptors, but several group exhibitions are also included. A few of the catalogs include annotations regarding price and sale of the exhibited works. One theater program is inscribed to George Staempfli by the artist who designed the cover, Paul Delvaux.
  Exhibition Catalogs are arranged chronologically.
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1959-1962; (5 folders) (Box 5, Folder 31-35)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1963-1970; (8 folders) (Box 5, Folder 36-43)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1971-1979; (10 folders) (Box 5, Folder 44-53)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1980-1988; (10 folders) (Box 6, Folder 1-10)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Program, Theatre Royal de la Monnaie, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 12)